<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Dip･et</title>
  <subtitle>The ramblings of a developing web developer</subtitle>
  <id>http://dipet.me</id>
  <link href="http://dipet.me"/>
  <link href="http://dipet.me/feed.xml" rel="self"/>
  <updated>2018-10-26T01:00:00-04:00</updated>
  <author>
    <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
  </author>
  <entry>
    <title>SQL noSQL</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://dipet.me/blog/sqls/"/>
    <id>http://dipet.me/blog/sqls/</id>
    <published>2018-10-26T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-26T10:58:26-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;I’ve been working nearly exclusively with NoSQL databases because they’re a lot different than traditional SQL databases, and how you approach them feels very foreign to me to an uncomfortable degree. One of the things that I’m still wrapping my head around is associations and the fact that you don’t always necessarily make a new “table” for them. To give a more concrete example, I’m working on a Dribbble clone,  In a traditional SQL database I would approach creating the user table as the following:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The user table itself would consist of email, password for one table and the second table would be the “profile” table which would consist of the more personal information such as: location, twitter handle, background photo, profile photo, website, list of skills. A profile table &lt;code&gt;belongs to&lt;/code&gt; a user, and a user &lt;code&gt;has one&lt;/code&gt; profile (that is dependent on the user, thus if the user deletes her/his account the profile goes with it). With NoSQL databases, it’s not necessary to create another table to handle this association and can be embedded within the user document without much worry. Embedding the profile is the best approach for the profile because the profile is definite in the number of objects in it (create a separate document if you expect the size of said document to grow example being: storing user all a user’s comments).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s definitely taken some time to really wrap my head around this, and even on this I’ve found myself questioning “do I need to even embed” I find myself asking this due to the added complexity that comes with embedding and trying to both populate and query against embedded data. If you take a my commits for (Chirpper)[https://github.com/diope/chirpper) you’ll see I go back and forth between embedding the profile and keeping it on the same depth as the rest of the user document.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s an interesting challenge working with NoSQL, in some ways it feels familiar to SQL databases (mostly in how you query data, it’s quite similar to most SQL ORMs), unfortunately I miss the power that comes with knowing SQL and being able to use that to be more nuanced (and performance minded) if necessary. I do not look forward to learning normalization techniques for NoSQL DB given how long it’s taken me to really get used to SQL databases techniques. That and I still find myself thinking of everything as SQL associations and joins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honestly I prefer SQL databases (postgreSQL is bae!) but I do appreciate a few things about NoSQLs mostly the fact I can edit data much quicker, no migrations needed, you can even directly edit documents on the fly which in some cases makes troubleshooting easier.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>mininotes</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://dipet.me/projects/mininotes-ohyea/"/>
    <id>http://dipet.me/projects/mininotes-ohyea/</id>
    <published>2018-10-12T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-12T14:53:44-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="ooooh awww" src="https://user-images.githubusercontent.com/3039981/46878777-1d3bed80-ce12-11e8-9e1b-5a0d8a8a8f22.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;mininotes is a very small appilication I created because I wanted a simple note taking app that lived in the menubar. Prior to creating this, I was using evernote&amp;rsquo;s app which was a lot of app just to use one small portion (and I had to make an account among other things, le sigh). I&amp;rsquo;ll be adding more to the application, mostly setting a global keybinding to invoke the app when it&amp;rsquo;s not the focus, and menu icon highlight when active.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote about creating it &lt;a href="http://www.dipet.me/blog/electron"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Enjoy the app!&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Electron Buildin</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://dipet.me/blog/electron/"/>
    <id>http://dipet.me/blog/electron/</id>
    <published>2018-10-11T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-17T12:12:56-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So I created another app for macOS mininote (available: &lt;a href="https://github.com/Diope/miniNotes/releases"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;), the reason I created this is simple&amp;hellip;I have a convoluted process for making small notes or pasting them from my clipboard and it involves alfred -&amp;gt; textedit.app -&amp;gt; cmd+p or jotting down my note. Or sometimes I&amp;rsquo;ll open up the note app. But honestly I really got tired of doing that, and I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to keep either of them in my dock if only purely for aesthetics (I am chuckling as I write this). So I decided why not make a small scratchpad app that will live in my menu bar. I did some surface level searching for one, and came across evernote&amp;rsquo;s application but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want all the other crap it came with. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t trying to organize, sort, and archive my notes. I literally just wanted something I could quickly cmd+v something into or jot down random note and then go about my day until I needed it again. I figured, why not build it, how hard could it be?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It wasn&amp;rsquo;t really hard, but it was involved. First question what language I was going to write this in. I actually early on thought about doing it with Swift (and honestly might do a rewrite), but then I thought what if I want to distribute it on Windows because I run into the same issue there despite the fact that nowadays I only use my Windows machine to play games on Steam/Uplay/Origin. I&amp;rsquo;ve created two tiny apps with C# and .NET but I didn&amp;rsquo;t want to have to create one version of my app on macOS in Swift then another for windows in C#, that&amp;rsquo;s way too much work for my small app. So that left the only logical choice, Javascript and using Electron. There was also Java but&amp;hellip;no. Don&amp;rsquo;t get me wrong, Java as a language is cool I guess, but yea no.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a few issues with Electron, mostly memory management. After learning C/C++, the various *allocs, pointers and referencing (not saying I&amp;rsquo;m a pro but I understand now). I&amp;rsquo;ve grown a great appreciation for performant, efficient code.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am familiar with Electron as I&amp;rsquo;ve made an app with it previously called &lt;a href="https://github.com/Diope/Readr/releases"&gt;Reader&lt;/a&gt;, despite how it looks, it was pretty simple when you break it down. The hardest parts were related to interaction because I only used CSS/HTML for that instead of a UI framework like React or Vue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this project I decided I would use React, I&amp;rsquo;m familiar with it and feel confident enough that I can get something simple like mininotes to play nice. I will go into detail in another post on all of the things I did, this post serves mostly to write what I learned creating this app.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First thing I learned: Ejecting&amp;hellip;still no reason to it at all! React build is still going to be your friend as it allows you to update as React receives updates. Another thing I learned&amp;hellip;sometimes documentation isn&amp;rsquo;t the most clear from the examples given. I didn&amp;rsquo;t git commit them but I assure I spent a good week or two slamming my head against my machine trying to figure out why I couldn&amp;rsquo;t get menu icons to show up using Electron-Builder but everything worked with Electron-Packager.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finding a React Markdown component was fairly simple, I started with React-Ace but I was searching for a way to do inline text manipulation without needing a second screen and it seemed like I had to jump through hoops to get React-Ace to do the basics of that, though I did like the various languages it would parse, if the need for more arised. So I kept looking until I stumbled upon React-SimpleMDE. It allowed same window editing but had editor icons associated with it. That was no problem, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d just hack them out (which I proceeded to do until seeing the option to remove it lol). Did the neessary React setup (creating an handleChange&amp;hellip;handler and setting the text to the user passed value). Even though I&amp;rsquo;m decent with React, I quite often find myself forgetting some of the basics and needing to consult other projects I&amp;rsquo;ve done to remind myself (es un poco molesto). Once I got that working, I was essentially done as I didn&amp;rsquo;t need to pass the data back to electron as React was responsible for the UI (this will also make persistence straightfoward later, if I choose to implement it).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From here I spent time styling the app (admittedly it wasn&amp;rsquo;t a whole bunch to style but still I I needed it to look nice), most of my time was spent on logo and menu icon design more than anything, I&amp;rsquo;m not trying to set the world on fire and win awards so I kept it simple, only doing three sketches before I opened Sketch and went to work. Now that I had that out of the way, it was time to package the app. Sidenote: I settled on 32x32 for the @2x menu icon size, and 16x16 for the @1x, in case anyone is reading this and wants to know the dimensions. I tried larger (44x44) but it looked entirely too big and had no padding so it sat at the edge of the top and bottom of the menubar, and it just looked hilariously out of place next to my other menubar apps&amp;rsquo; icons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now it&amp;rsquo;s time to package this sucker, I initially decided on using Electron-Packager for this figuring that Electron-Builder was for more complex applications (I am not sure WHY I thought this), something I didn&amp;rsquo;t realise until this app was that Electron-Packager with it&amp;rsquo;s default settings just shoves the entire project folder as it is into your .dmg file, which is like holy shit why?! As a result of this, my app was over 700mb in size&amp;hellip;yea that was unacceptable, I was determined to get Electron-Builder to work, Electron apps are already huge because they require chrominium instance to run and that&amp;rsquo;s 40MB by itself. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where I messed up with Electron-Builder: The &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; section of &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;; looking at various examples online, I thought the only thing I needed was my &lt;code&gt;build&lt;/code&gt; directory that is produced by yarn/react build command. But this isn&amp;rsquo;t actually correct, I pretty much forgot that build will only produce code related to React (I know I know how did I forget this lol) so for a good 4 days, I sat in frustration wondering why things weren&amp;rsquo;t working when I packaged the app but worked fine when I ran &lt;code&gt;electron .&lt;/code&gt;. I didn&amp;rsquo;t have to do any of this with Readr because again it was CSS/HTML in the sense of not using a UI framework that utilized webpack or Rollup.js, or anything. Just a couple of files contained within the same folder (note to self, go back and separate things into different folders honestly). So once the lightbulb went out that reminded me I needed to include my electron folder (for two of those days, I honestly thought it was the way I was naming my folder containing my electron code 😂). So I had to tell Electron-Builder the folders it needs, which looks like&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre class="highlight javascript"&gt;&lt;code&gt;  &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"build"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;{&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"files"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;:&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;[&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"build/**/* (this is the react build folder and all it's sub-folders)"&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;,&lt;/span&gt;
      &lt;span class="s2"&gt;"electron/**/*"&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;all&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;my&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;electron&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;code&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;and&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;sub&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;-&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;folders&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="s2"&gt;",
      "&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;assets&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="cm"&gt;/**/&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="o"&gt;*&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="p"&gt;(&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="nx"&gt;contains&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;the&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="nx"&gt;obvious&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="p"&gt;)&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="err"&gt;"&lt;/span&gt;
    &lt;span class="p"&gt;]&lt;/span&gt;
  &lt;span class="p"&gt;}&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ran Electron-builder and&amp;hellip;nope, so close! An error slightly unrelated to my project, I got a node error regarding fsevents, which was not resolved by npm installing it, well fuck so what do I do? Well apparently I could get around it by simply running the same command via yarn&amp;hellip;I don&amp;rsquo;t understand exacly why that I but honestly I didn&amp;rsquo;t research into it too much, this was supposed to be a weekend project that ended up becoming a two week project smh. 
(Note: the project was longer than the github log suggests, I duplicated the folder later and setup a new git).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So the build is now working? No, apparently Electron-builder could not find &lt;code&gt;main.js&lt;/code&gt; despite the fact I specified it in my &lt;code&gt;package.json&lt;/code&gt;, some internet searching told me to add &lt;code&gt;homepage:&amp;#39;./&amp;#39;&lt;/code&gt; to my package.json file, alright. So I tried that&amp;hellip;and no dice. Hmm, well that addtion does make sense, as it would tell Electron what the entry point is for the app but yet it produces nothing. So some more digging on the interwebs taught me about Electron-Builder&amp;rsquo;s metadata option, which basically let&amp;rsquo;s you inject a file during the build project. After conflicting information on the correct syntax to use, which was &lt;code&gt;-c.extraMetadata.main=electron/main.js&lt;/code&gt; (in my case the main.js was located in the electron folder). Again I emphasis that &lt;code&gt;electron/main.js&lt;/code&gt; is specified as the starting point, which is fine for Electron itself (running &lt;code&gt;electron .&lt;/code&gt; produces no issues), but apparently means nothing to Electron-Builder? Anyways, that option fixes it. But I the npm fsevents issue popped back up. So I created a script called &lt;code&gt;electron-pack&lt;/code&gt; to build the app using the aforementioned flag and much like last time it worked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Alright, so everything builds and actually runs! Yatta, but one final issue stood in my way, Mojave came out and I introduced a dark mode. So now I had to figure out how to account for people using the dark mode menu bar, scheiße! I sat for about an hour searching through Electron documentation for API hooks for Mojave&amp;rsquo;s dark mode. I figured it&amp;rsquo;d be a pretty simple if statement, dark mode ? dark menubar icon : light menubar icon. I ended up finding out it was even more simple than that! Because I&amp;rsquo;ve always used dark mode (and prior a dark menu bar) I created the mininote icon in white&amp;hellip;which is wrong. All I had to do was create the icon in #000 black, and make sure the file name ended with &lt;code&gt;Template.png&lt;/code&gt; ex: &lt;code&gt;trayIconTemplate.png&lt;/code&gt;, and macOS takes care of making it white when used with dark mode, or leaving the icon as it&amp;rsquo;s default black when used in light mode.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So that&amp;rsquo;s the basic run down of the creation of this app, or rather some of the random hangups I had while creating it.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Drubbble</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://dipet.me/projects/drubbble/"/>
    <id>http://dipet.me/projects/drubbble/</id>
    <published>2018-09-14T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2019-01-22T20:34:18-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;So this is actually an older project, this was my test playground for learning Rails, I would create small toy projects and then implement them into this project, I worked on it on and off for a couple of years. Even though it&amp;rsquo;s old, out of all the things I&amp;rsquo;ve made I am still the most proud of this. So over the weekend I decided to troubleshoot and update it enough to at least getting it running on Heroku. Working on troubleshooting was actually pretty fun, I hadn&amp;rsquo;t done any Ruby or rails work in years and getting back into the flow of things was very easy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had much to update to get it running on heroku, I will document sokme of the process in another post, this post is to talk about what features I implemented. As any one can see this was based on an older design of Dribbble before their big update in 2017. Unforunately as of this post I no longer have any screenshots of Dribbble&amp;rsquo;s old layout to compare and contrast with my drubbble project but I strived for near 1:1 in nearly all aspects. That alone was quite a bit of fun from a styling/SASS perspective. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I implemented the most important part of Dribbble in my recreation which was the ability to create an account and upload photos. There was much I learned on this feature which really served as a great bed rock of general computer science principles. My main take away was relational databases (from here I went on to learn and practice both SQL but also database normalization). I was fascinated by how associations, primary keys all worked together and learned exactly what ORMs were doing, where their strengths were and were they struggled compared to using SQL directly. Also learned QUITE about authenticiation/authorization what the differences are, how it works on a fundamental level (I will admit to getting sidetracked from the project for a month or two to learn this indepth) and why rolling your own authentication/authorization implementation is a TERRIBLE idea (I rolled by own in toy apps and saw how easy they were to break). One of the parts I&amp;rsquo;m most proud of building is the &lt;code&gt;:after&lt;/code&gt; feature once the user made their account the profile portion was auto populated with generic/empty data for the user to fill in at a later time. Creating this feature allowed me to get a feel for HOW to search through documentation to problem solve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another feature I was proud of implementing was the tags system which ended up functioning exactly the same as Dribbble&amp;rsquo;s, I was proud of this mostly because in order for me to figure it out I had to actually sit down and draw out the database relationship in order to implement it, at first I thought that was a sign of me not understanding database design enough to implement it correct without the &amp;lsquo;help&amp;rsquo; of a diagram but soon realized that, database diagrams are absolutely common and it would be amateurish if I DIDN&amp;rsquo;T have a diagram. Created the ability to view all posts from any tag, within their own page. The tagging system was a pain because at no point did I think to unify the tags, so in the first go around, I had tags with different formatting, it was a simple fix but still funny looking back because at the time I definitely ran my hands through my hair if I remember correctly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Utilizing what I learned from the tagging system, I was able to go forward and add a followers/following system in the vein of Twitter&amp;rsquo;s to mimick the same feature from Dribbble. Looking back I could have implemented it a bit better from an ORM/database perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I could go on about the numerous lessons I learned creating this and as I stated much of it helped improve my fundamental computer science knowledge which I am forever grateful, because of this project I found it hilarious easy to learn new technologies, this project also served as the starting point for me realising I was curious about computer science as a whole topic, I went on to teaching myself C++ and more specifically memory management (I had to know how pointers worked, so I started learning C, malloc, alloc, etc). &lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Drybbble? Drybbble</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://dipet.me/projects/drybbble/"/>
    <id>http://dipet.me/projects/drybbble/</id>
    <published>2018-09-14T01:00:00-04:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-12T15:13:31-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;Drybbble is an current project that will essentially be a Dribbble clone made with MongoDB/Express/Node.js that generates API endpoints paired with React for the UI (and I will be making a second that uses Vue.js). I have previously recreated Dribbble, calling it &lt;a href="https://github.com/diope/drubbble"&gt;Drubbble&lt;/a&gt; using Rails 4.2 back in 2016-2017 (I will be updating that to Rails 5 in the second half of Dec when I have free time). Initially I was going to use PostgreSQL because I&amp;rsquo;m very comfortable with SQL commands, associations, and normalization/denormalization so I decided to instead use MongoDB, which I&amp;rsquo;ve only used in tutorial and toy app capacity, and I like the challenge&amp;hellip;and oh what a challenge it has been!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will do a write up on what I&amp;rsquo;ve learned so far at a later date.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
  <entry>
    <title>Malloc, Calloc, Realloc Free Oh My!</title>
    <link rel="alternate" href="http://dipet.me/blog/memory-allocation/"/>
    <id>http://dipet.me/blog/memory-allocation/</id>
    <published>2018-02-11T00:00:00-05:00</published>
    <updated>2018-10-12T15:51:20-04:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Dion Pettaway</name>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;For the last 4ish months, I&amp;rsquo;ve dived head first into a topic I&amp;rsquo;ve been very excited to get to that is C/C++ and managing memory. To preface this, I am by no means an expert but I do enjoy the subject and how vast it is. I spent a large portion of time wrapping my head around pointers and referenccing/derefeencing, before moving on to malloc and calloc. As I&amp;rsquo;ve started learning about memory management in C/C++ I&amp;rsquo;ve naturally had to pick up on heap versus stack, and this in itself helped a few data structures click as well as how applications use memory and memory leaks (it seems simple to call &lt;code&gt;free()&lt;/code&gt; when necessary but I can easily see why mistakes are made.)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To refresh; Heap is used for dynamic memory allocation (both heap and stack use/are stored in your machine&amp;rsquo;s RAM). You should consider using the heap when you&amp;rsquo;re going to be allocating a lot of memory, and allocating it a run time. As far as I understand and have learned, it&amp;rsquo;s best to use heap when you plan to keep that variable around for a long time, or alternatively for variables that need to dynamically allocate their memory (arrays y structs!)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Stacks on the other hand should be allocated at compile time and you shouldn&amp;rsquo;t allocate a lot of memory to them, stacks are only available to threads, but you can access the stack very quickly. Variables allocated on the stack should for all intents and purposes have a very short shelf life, most say anything created on the stack shouldn&amp;rsquo;t stick around after it&amp;rsquo;s been invoked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still have much to learn with malloc, calloc, realloc, free and my end goal is creating my own basic garbage collector to really solidify my learnings.&lt;/p&gt;
</content>
  </entry>
</feed>
